And I'm going to start off with the header.
Today is March 6, 2026.
My name is Caitlin Sheets, and I'm here with Dr. Angela Hudson.
We're conducting this interview in the Glasscock Building of Campus in Texas A&M University in College Station, Texas.
The interview is part of an oral history project documenting the experiences of Aggies for the 150th celebration of Texas A&M.
And do I have consent to record this for you?
Yes, you do.
Awesome.
Thank you so much.
First, can you give me a little bit of a biographical background on yourself, where you grew up,
where you went to college, that kind of thing?
So I was born in Spartanburg, South Carolina, which is in the Piedmont upstate.
And I moved around several times when I was a kid.
So I lived for about seven years in Monroe, Louisiana.
Lived for about seven years in Spartanburg.
And two years in Memphis, Tennessee, which is where I graduated high school.
I went to college for my undergraduate degree at Auburn University in Alabama.
And I majored in English and Spanish.
Wow.
And then I went to get my master's degree at the University of Georgia, also in the English department.
And moved then from Athens, Georgia, to New Haven, Connecticut, which is where I did my Ph.D. in American Studies.
And when I graduated with my Ph.D. in 2007, I had been offered a job here in the Department of History at Texas A&M.
And I've been here ever since.
So you've always been here for 20 years.
It'll be 19 years this June.
That's wild.
You must have seen so many changes between when you first got here to now.
The city has changed a lot.
Both Bryan and College Station have changed a lot.
Campus has changed.
There have been a lot of different developments in the department, the college, the former college, new college, different leadership.
So it's been a really interesting almost 20 years.
Yeah.
If I could back up a second, you said you were English in your undergrad.
How did you go from English to history?
Yeah, I like to tell people that I'm, you know,
There's an old commercial where this man would say, I'm not a doctor, I just play one on TV.
And so I sort of say that about being a historian.
So I actually have no degrees in history.
My degrees are English and Spanish.
My master's is in English with focus on American literature.
And my PhD is in American studies, which has a strong historical component.
But it also includes training in anthropology, sociology, literature, literary studies.
But my advisor was a historian, and my path to history started when I was studying literature, and specifically Native American literature.
I took my first Native American literature course when I was an undergrad at Auburn, and I was just fascinated.
It was a genre, it was an approach to literature that I had never encountered before.
And I found that it was difficult for me sometimes to understand
the topics that were being discussed in the literature because i didn't have very much historical context okay so you know reading a book like leslie marmon silko's ceremony which is one of these canonical books in in american literature and specifically native american literature and she's writing about a navajo soldier who comes back to his reservation after world war ii and is grappling with a variety of the after effects of
the war, but also the reality of uranium mining on and around the reservation.
And this was just something I'd never learned in any kind of history class.
So as I proceeded into my master's working on American literature, I studied Native American literature even more, as well as African American and Asian American and Latin American literature.
And I just wanted to know what had happened in these various time periods that inspired writers to write what they were producing.
So I started making a nuisance of myself and going over to the history department and knocking on doors and asking professors, this was at University of Georgia, to explain things to me so that I could understand the literature.
And by the time I got into my PhD program, I took a little break between master's and PhD, and I worked at the Digital Library of Georgia
grant-funded database project that was very archival, very much about the sort of original archival research.
And then between those two things, I was hooked.
Between listening to the history professors tell me what I needed to know to understand the literature and spending eight hours a day with documents
and creating an online accessible version of these documents, then I was really hooked with historical research.
That's so interesting.
You said that you've never read anything or heard anything like the stories.
What was different about those stories?
So I think just at first, I mean, the first thing is that there was just not a lot in my experience in my educational curriculum growing up about Native Americans at all.
Mm-hmm.
when they were discussed, it was always in the past tense, as if they sort of lived long ago and don't live now, right?
And as a person who grew up all around the South, if Native people, if American Indians did come up in conversation, it was oftentimes that someone would say, oh, my great-grandmother's Cherokee, right?
There are lots of claims that I learned later were mostly spurious claims to Native ancestries.
And so when I started reading these books, books that were set in the late 19th century in the Great Lakes, books by Louise Erdrich and others, I just thought, I know nothing about the belief systems.
I know nothing about these really diverse groups of American Indians.
The Silco book I referenced, it's post-World War II.
If you had just trusted the curriculum that I had been exposed to as a child,
American Indians didn't make it out of the 19th century, right?
So even just knowing that they were veterans of World War II, that their communities were grappling with resource extraction and environmental degradation and pollution in the modern era.
These were just things I had never confronted before.
Indians were people in the movies, in the westerns, and people of the past, right?
Whether they were somebody's alleged ancestor or in some kind of storybook.
That makes sense.
So it was just filling in those gaps in my education.
Right.
So it seems like you're really, you took it upon yourself to go out there and find these things.
And is that kind of just your personality to do that?
Or is that how you go about other things too in your life?
I think so.
I think I always want to know why I don't know something.
Mm-hmm.
So when I realize that I don't know something, the first thing is sort of to acknowledge, well, I didn't know that.
But I'm very quick and have always been very quick to say, well, why didn't I know that?
And then to try and figure out where that gap came from.
In some cases, even today, I learn things from my kids learning physics.
I didn't know that.
Why didn't I know that?
Well, because I don't like physics as a subject in school.
I didn't like it as a subject in school, so it wasn't something that I pursued.
Sometimes the answers are really straightforward.
But in other cases, it has led me to question how we teach,
um you know american history how we teach global history why is it that certain topics are you can count on them being included every single time and then other topics are if they're brought up it's only in very limited quantities and with a very specific kind of perspective so that why piece of it i think is often the thing that sets me off on a path to figure out
You know, where did this drop out of the narrative?
Right.
And why is that so?
That's interesting.
And you're talking about that, the way things are presented and the way you learn about things.
From the beginning of your career to now, how have you seen those changes on whether it's the narrative or whatever's being taught?
Have you seen changes in that?
Yeah.
A little bit.
I mean, I guess in some ways it's kind of sad to say I haven't seen a lot of changes.
When students come into my classroom here at Texas A&M, they're often just as surprised as I was to learn some of these topics.
And they will frequently say to me or write in their, you know, assignments,
I never learned this before.
And then many of them will very quickly follow up with, why did I never learn this before, right?
Which is, and it's sad to say that that is still a problem, I think, in how we, in the historical narratives that we choose to share and prioritize.
But my own curiosity about why didn't I know things
I think helps me when I'm teaching, because when students tell me I never learned this before, why did I never learn this before?
That then becomes an opportunity for us to talk about kind of the meta history.
Why do we know what we know and why do we not know what we don't know?
And I always ask my students when they when we start talking about, for example,
Indian removal is a topic that I teach about in my classes pretty frequently.
And that's one topic, the Trail of Tears, that students have confronted in their schooling.
But it's usually the last topic that they ever addressed in terms of Native American history.
Right.
And so we talk about, well, what's at stake with that being your last real lesson on Native peoples?
Yeah.
Right?
So that goes to that impression that I had received of Native American people being people of the past.
They're not modern people.
They didn't come with us into the modern age and progress.
That's the impression that that leaves.
So I think the K-12 curriculum is limited because there's only so much you can do.
There's only so much time.
The demands of things like standardized tests put a lot of pressure on teachers.
Yeah.
And even teachers who are very well prepared, teachers who I've taught, you know, and my colleagues in the history department have taught and they've gone on and made their careers in education come back and report frustration with, you know, they've taken these history classes, they want to teach these things, but structurally within the school system, it's often really difficult to find the time for it.
So as a consequence, we end up still getting students at the college level who are frequently uninformed about some of these topics.
which is a great teaching opportunity, but I'd rather not have them have those gaps, even though it's an opportunity for us in terms of learning.
That makes sense.
I did a little background research just because I wanted to see your body of work.
I came across The Real Native Genius.
That one was so interesting to me as an outsider because of the ideas of identity and presentation of yourself.
For people listening, it's the story of a formerly enslaved man and a white man
white woman who claimed to be native american that's right how did you come across that story um mostly accidentally but it but it fits with that timeline that i gave you in the beginning i was talking about my education um so when i was studying literature in my master's program i was taking a course on african-american autobiography and so we were reading things like um
up from slavery, Frederick Douglass, Booker T. Washington, Richard Wright, Ann Moody, Malcolm X, a bunch of classics.
We also read this book called The Life of Okatubby.
And this was an annotated edition of a couple of versions of an autobiography mashed together about a man who was born in Natchez, Mississippi, who was born into slavery,
in the early part of the 19th century, around 1810, 1811, and ultimately built a life for himself as a performer who claimed a Native American persona and performed that persona in various contexts.
I thought it was fascinating.
I was like, I want to work on this, but ultimately, you know, I went and started working on some other topics after taking that class in my dissertation,
was in a different direction.
My dissertation was about the Creek Indian people and present-day Georgia and Alabama between the late 18th century and the era of removal.
When I finished that project, I said, I'm going to go back to this really interesting fellow, Okotubby.
And I started researching him some more, and literally things fell out of the sky into my lap.
People contacted me when I started giving conference presentations about him,
and said, do you know about this?
Do you know about that?
Did you know about his Mormon period?
And I said, his what?
And that was when I started to realize that this was not just a story about an African-American person who claims to be Native American, which is kind of the way it has often been framed in the historiography.
His wife was a white woman who claimed to be Native, claimed to be Mohawk.
Most of the people who had written about both of them up to this point believed her claims.
Most of the people writing from that angle of his autobiography believed that she was Mohawk, and the real questions were around him.
When I discovered that there was this whole other body of literature about her and her family, and they were actually a white family from upstate New York who were among the first converts to the new Mormon faith, then I said, I've got a whole different story on my hands here.
And then I began to kind of bring these two bodies of sources together to tell this crazy story that even when I was writing it, sometimes I thought, this is unbelievable.
They worked for P.T.
Barnum.
They traveled all around the United States.
They had private audiences with Brigham Young on the eve of him becoming the president of the church.
you know, she was arrested for manslaughter and spent nine years in Sing Sing.
Oh my goodness.
So they had a really, really wild life, but I used their lives and specifically their performance of Native American persona to make an argument about the flexibility, but also the limits of what I call Indian-ness in the middle of the 19th century, like roughly in the Annabella period and then shortly after.
I didn't even realize there was a time period where people would go around on road shows.
I've obviously never learned that, but that's fascinating to me.
That's like a whole genre.
Yeah, and they drew a lot of their inspiration and kind of modeled themselves in some ways on...
Native people who were on either the lecture circuit or the performance circuit of some kind.
So there was a genre and it had its own kind of character.
And they sort of moved in and out of it.
Sometimes they were a little bit more on the serious side, like kind of giving lectures, temperance lectures, that sort of thing.
But then other times it was, you know, musical performances and joke telling.
And it kind of, they were very,
Sort of like chameleons, what their audience wanted, they were willing to provide.
And that original autobiography that set me on this path, it turned out, was actually written by her.
Oh, okay.
About his life.
But the more I learned about her life, the more I could see the traces of her life, actually, in that autobiography.
So truly more of a composite story.
self-narrative than it is just a story of his life.
That's fascinating.
Did, did she write that under a different name or actually her own name?
No, it was under a different name.
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
At the beginning of the book, I have a list of aliases for both of them because over the course of, over time they use, I think each one of them had at least a dozen aliases.
So it was sort of like being a private investigator when I was working on this or a detective.
because frequently I had to identify who were their known accomplices or their known contacts and then follow those people around.
Besides the autobiography, she left two letters that I've been able to locate, and that's it.
There were no other primary sources that were from them directly.
So newspaper accounts, city directories, court cases, criminal cases.
published accounts of other people who circulated in their orbit.
Everything was really about the impressions that they left on the world that they lived in.
So it sounds like archives were a big part of your research and also this time of your life.
Absolutely.
And I think many historians, when we work on a long-form project,
are going to a particular library or repository archive and spending weeks, maybe months, in the same collection.
Especially people who are working on a single individual.
This project was quite different than that.
Because I was, in effect, chasing them around the continent, I was frequently going to multiple archives in a single week.
There would be just small things that I was looking for.
Needles in a haystack.
In some cases, or in many cases, it was I would know if they had it or not very quickly.
So in some ways, sometimes the archivists really did not like to see me coming because I was that patron who would request 40 things in one day and then say, nope, I don't need it.
I could look at them really quickly and see whether or not they were going to have what I was looking for.
So I got in a habit of just apologizing when I got there and saying, I'm going to be that person who makes you go back to the stacks multiple times.
I think you're the fun kind of patron, though, because that's fun to me.
Well, you know, I was so enthralled with these two individuals myself.
I do think that my enthusiasm was kind of infectious because there were a couple of places that I worked and I would tell them what I was working on, you know.
And I would use that to explain, I'm going to request all this stuff, and I may not spend a lot of time with each source, and I promise you I know what I'm doing.
And I would tell them what I was looking for.
And a lot of times I didn't find what I was looking for, but when I did, I was so excited, and they would get excited, and we'd be high-fiving over the public services desk.
So it was a lot of fun.
And I got to do research in some places that I had never thought would be...
you know, germane to my study of doing research in the City of Toronto archives, in the Archives of Ontario, at the LDS Church History Library in Salt Lake City, at Bram Young University, so literally all across the continent doing this research.
I knew there was like a Mormon part of this.
How did, like, how was that experience going to the LDS archives and stuff like that?
Because I just, I'm just trying to like picture that.
It was fantastic.
I mean, so this was not a part of the story that I knew was going to be there.
Right.
So I wasn't trained in like Mormon history, LDS history.
Although my advisor,
And graduate school was really a Western Americanist.
So I had had some exposure to some of the historiography, but it had not been my focus.
So one of the first things that I had to do when I realized that this was going to be a major part of the book was I had to do my homework.
I had to read in that subfield.
And I had some friends introduce me to scholars of LDS history.
But I also then made some cold calls and said, this is what I'm doing, can you help me?
I need to figure out what I need to be reading, what collections I should be looking at.
And that's how I then figured out which collections I needed to see, for example, at the Harold Lee Library at BYU and at the church library in Salt Lake City.
and more generous and welcoming group of scholars and researchers I couldn't have found anywhere.
That's so nice to hear.
These folks were so, so kind and patient because I didn't know what I didn't know.
And there were lots and lots of things just about the theology and the doctrinal aspects that I needed to have at least a basic understanding of so that I could recognize what I was seeing in some of these sources.
And yeah, I mean, it was just a wonderful experience.
It restored my faith in, you know, the humanity of scholars to help each other out.
And so I will admit to being intimidated going into that and feeling very much like an outsider and that I would be treated with suspicion or as an outsider.
at least in those research contexts and in those scholarly circles, I never was.
People were very generous and very open, and I couldn't have written the book without their help.
Wow.
That's lovely to hear, though, because I also, like, if I went to do that because I knew nothing about it, I also would be very, like, oh, no.
Yeah, I was very aware of my own
subject position.
But as a historian, as a researcher, it's really good to be reminded that our identities are not universal, that we have subject positions and those subject positions are in many cases going to dictate our access to things.
And so it was, you know, it was a good reminder, I think.
um if i could switch gears a little bit um whenever you first started work here in 2007 you said 2007 um what was that like what was like uh your first experiences here like so when i was hired my position was specifically advertised for american indian history so i was really lucky that i actually landed a job in my area of specialty um and so my first semester i came in and taught
you know, a course right in my content area.
And within the first couple of years, I was teaching a large lecture course on American Indian history, which in our curriculum, at least right now, students can take that instead of taking 105 or 106, which are the US history survey courses.
So this course counts for US history credit so far.
But it made it really fun to teach in comparison to those US surveys.
that students have to take because the students in my class had self-selected to take this particular approach to US history.
So they had a certain level of interest and enthusiasm that is probably not the case for all the students just taking their core curriculum requirements.
One of the things that surprised me early on was that when I taught in my first lecture class, and I'm in the big lecture hall, sort of stadium seating, I'm down at the podium, first day of class, I'm super nervous.
Teaching is one of those things that you have to practice.
The nerves never completely go away, but it gets better.
First day of class, you know, go over the syllabus, expectations, and so on.
When I ended class, students came and lined up next to the podium to shake my hand and tell me their name and tell me why they were interested in the class.
And everyone was so polite.
I mean, it wasn't all the students in the class, but it was, you know,
15, 20 out of a class of maybe 200.
That's a lot.
And just wanted to say hi, ma'am.
Just want to say howdy and welcome.
And I'm so glad to be in your class.
And that kind of hospitality and that politeness is something that I still see in our students.
And I think it's a real asset most of the time.
Students can be quite deferential to their professors.
Which is good because a lot of times you don't deal with a lot of misbehavior, quote-unquote.
I mean, they're adults and we're adults, but in some college contexts there could be issues.
Where it is a little challenging, and I learned the first couple of times I taught courses with a significant discussion component, is that students can be a little bit shy to disagree with each other.
Because they're trying to be polite and respectful, and I absolutely appreciate that.
We should have polite, respectful discussions.
But also, you want them to engage.
You want them to push back, to question each other, to question themselves, to question me.
So over time, I've developed a few strategies, and usually it's to get them to have solidarity amongst each other against me.
So when I teach the course I developed on American Indians in Southern history, which is one of my areas of specialty,
I go in on the first day and we talk about what is the South, where is the South, when is the South, and how do we define the answers to those questions.
And food ways, it's one of the ways that we define that or we answer it.
So we talk about what are some Southern foods and they shout out some things.
And then I say, I throw down the gauntlet and I say, I'm from South Carolina, brisket is not barbecue.
Barbecue is pork, fight me.
And then that helps because even the most quiet students have an opinion about barbecue, typically.
And so then they'll turn to each other and say, what is she saying?
This is blasphemy.
So you figure out ways to get them past the initial deference and shyness that might keep them from engaging in those conversations.
But yeah, those are a few of my memories from the first couple of years.
Now that the changes before COVID to during COVID, what were, I mean, obviously you had to go online, but what were some of the other differences that you saw?
Yeah.
So I think in terms of student expectations, I think that one of the changes I've seen, and it's hard for me to know whether this is fully attributable to COVID or if it's just a generational shift because I have been here almost 20 years.
So, you know, there've been, we,
there's been at least one kind of generational shift in that time between the, from the student perspective.
Um, I think students, not all of them, but I think more students now, um, expect a certain level of handholding, um, that some of it may be attributable to COVID because during COVID without being in the school,
structure you know day-to-day in person and without all of the infrastructure that went with it there was a lot more material given to students right for them to sort of engage with and then the teaching part i'm you know doing scare quotes here the teaching part was was often just making sure they understood the stuff that you had already given them
And I think that's quite different than how many of us were teaching before COVID.
So then afterwards, and again, not sure if this is really caused by it or if this just kind of emphasized it or amplified it, but I think there's more of an expectation now that all the lectures will be online, all the slides will be provided.
The questions are going to be provided before the test, that kind of thing.
And I think there's some pedagogical value to some of those things, but I think some of them also developed as like a habit and as an expectation.
So from my perspective, instructors are frequently in this moment in 2026 trying to navigate that and figure out how to moderate
students' expectations.
Right.
But also, you know, meet them, if not where they are, you know, close to where they are.
Yeah.
And then try to take them where you want them to be.
So that's something.
In terms of working at the university since COVID, I mean, the expectation that everyone is online all the time, everyone is available for meetings or calls,
you know, just hop on a Teams call, just hop on a Zoom call, and it's, you know, that, I think, is exhausting, and it also is very counterproductive in terms of scholarship, but also other work that we do, such as teaching and grading and all of that.
Yeah, I didn't even think about that part of it.
It's just become so natural and normal now.
Right, it's very normalized now, yeah, to the point that I think, you know, at some point,
maybe in the future, we're going to have to say, okay, these are like my non-meeting hours during the workday.
I mean, even during the workday.
I don't mean after the workday ends, but even during the workday, these are my non-teams, Zoom, phone call.
I will be working.
Your quiet hours for you.
Exactly.
I will be working, doing things.
I will not be in meetings during these times.
That brings up the question of how do you balance having to always be there online, ready to answer a phone, ready to answer your email, and then your personal home life?
Because that has to bleed together somehow.
Yeah, it does.
I mean, I, for many years, until I became department head in 2023, I was pretty successful at blocking off my weekends.
Mm-hmm.
And if I worked on the weekends, it was either because I was doing, I had a writing deadline, I was doing research and writing, or I had a grading deadline, and I had to get my grades done for my students.
But the rest of the time, there was no administrative work, even before I was a department head, you know, there was always sort of administrative-type tasks.
I never did those things on the weekend, and I was pretty good at maintaining that boundary.
I have two children.
When I moved here to take the position, my oldest
my now oldest child was 15 months old and my second child was born in 2010 and so you know my my kids have grown up with me in this department um and it's it's very important for me to have that separation right um i do think post-covid it's been harder to keep that separation it's one of the biggest things i noticed is people just expecting you to be available um and then since becoming a
and departmental administrator, department head, there are just things that I can't let them wait from Friday at 5 p.m. until Monday at 8 a.m.
I'm just going to have to address them because the situation might be urgent enough that I really can't let it fester.
over even a weekend.
That makes sense.
That brings up also the idea of how have your duties changed from just being a professor, not just a professor, but a professor to an administrative head of the department?
So one of the biggest things is that I am a manager.
And, you know, I was not trained as a manager.
I was trained as a historian, as a cultural studies scholar.
I was describing to you my research experiences, and that is mainly, except for when I'm high-fiving the archivist and I find something cool, that is mainly me with a book or a folder of documents sitting alone doing my work and thinking.
So being a department head is about managing people, and many of us who are scholars are not very good at that.
I mean, many of us who have entered this profession do so because we like being alone.
And we don't like being that kind of communicator.
And so learning what my management style is and figuring out how to implement that and how to mentor people, even people that I don't necessarily have a subject field relationship with, but as their supervisor and as their department leader, I still need to act in that mentoring position.
Right.
That's been an interesting journey for me.
I'm still on that journey, figuring out how I function as a manager.
In the past, I'd say, year and a half, one of the biggest differences is how much of my time I spend on compliance.
So there are so many different levels to a large state institution like this.
Oh, okay.
where the department head is charged with ensuring compliance.
And it starts with very basic things, very basic but important things like safety and trainings.
But it goes to every, it touches every aspect of the department's operation at this point.
It touches research.
I have to ensure compliance when faculty and graduate students are traveling to various places to do research.
There's all kinds of immigration and travel issues.
everything having to do with funding and budgets and disbursements of funds that all has to be done in particular ways where I have to certify through many, many levels that this is approved, that this is compliant with system policies, with state laws, federal laws.
And then more recently, the attention to the teaching materials is another layer of compliance work that I think most department heads
or at least many department heads, particularly in our college, the College of Arts and Sciences, are spending far more time this, you know, this April 2026, of more hours in our day doing compliance activities than we ever could have imagined even just a year ago.
And so...
That makes it harder to feel, to be enthusiastic and to feel inspired and to carry that inspiration about the amazing things that we do onto the faculty and the students.
So I'm cautiously optimistic that we'll figure out ways to make this smoother and less onerous.
But that's one of the biggest changes in the very recent past.
some difficult things I've never really had to think about.
There's a lot of clicking, a lot of approve, you know, approve, approve, approve, certify, certify, certify.
Is the way this department run, is it more of hierarchical or a democratic kind of?
It's pretty hierarchical.
I think most of the departments at this university are.
In a lot of universities and colleges, excuse me,
The department leader is the department chair, who kind of, that's a role that pretty much every senior professor in the department is going to take their turn rotating through.
And they have some decision-making power, but not unlimited power.
And a lot more of the heavy-duty decision-making happens maybe at the provost level or something adjacent to that.
The model we have here at A&M is that our department leaders are department heads, and they hold a lot more responsibility as department heads.
And a person may be a department head.
I know people have done this for 20-plus years.
So it's not necessarily the same thing where everybody's rotating through, therefore everybody kind of needs to be equally able to do the thing.
So it's pretty hierarchical.
I think that's true of the university in general.
I mean, that's true for deans and on.
But in our department, we do really strongly value shared governance and transparency.
That's something that's very important to me personally.
We have an elected executive committee that's representative of multiple ranks in the department, and that elected committee acts as an advisory board, essentially, to the department head.
So when I need to go and spend money on something, or someone comes to me and asks me to spend money on something, I go and consult the democratically elected executive committee about whether or not this is a wise use of departmental resources.
The decision of whether to do it is ultimately mine as the department head, and any consequences of that decision are also mine.
But I think it's smart for the faculty to feel very included and to have their input weighed
in that kind of decision making.
That makes sense.
And that brings me to the idea of how do you combat burnout?
Because you seem to be doing so much in so many different areas.
How do you state that life?
When I figure out, I'll tell you.
Oh no, oh no.
No, I mean, I think there's a couple of things.
One of the most important is that I take pains to remind myself why I got in this profession.
it's definitely not to click buttons to ensure compliance.
That is soul-sucking.
But I love the work that I do in terms of my research, in terms of my teaching.
I'm one of those weird souls who really likes writing, even though it's hard.
I like writing.
I consider myself, in some ways, first and foremost, a writer.
And so trying to make time to think ideas
instead of thinking about all the other things.
And in this department, that's not that hard because we have such cool stuff going on.
We've been hiring new faculty, going to their talks and listening to the work that they're currently focusing on.
Even just around the coffee machine, someone telling me they just came back from a conference and they heard a really interesting paper.
Thinking the ideas that remind me why I got into the profession helps to balance out
all of the other stuff.
But also spending time with my family and doing the things that I enjoy doing.
My family has a no history rule when we go on vacation.
So you might think a history professor would go to all the museums and historic sites and boy, I would love to.
But my family will often say, okay, either no history on this trip or you get one museum or one historic site.
but I always work around them wherever we go, especially, well, if it's somewhere we've never been before, I usually sneak and read a couple of books about the place before we go, and then while we're driving down the street, I'll say, oh, this road's named after, and I give them a little mini lecture, and yeah, so I manage to sneak it in.
That's funny.
But my family is really important to me, and I enjoy, they're my favorite people in the world.
I enjoy spending time with them more than any other humans on the planet.
It's lovely to hear.
How old are they now, your kids?
I have two sons.
One is 15 and one is 19.
Fun ages.
Yes, yeah.
And as I said, they've grown up on this campus pretty much, you know.
And in this department, I came into the department in 2007 with several other current faculty who are still here.
who had little ones and our kids have grown up together.
And now we've got a crop of younger faculty who have littles and their kids are growing up together.
That's so nice to hear, the community.
Yeah, it does foster a really nice feeling of community.
Something that I'm personally interested in is how professors are dealing, seeing how AI is affecting their work, class, students.
Has there been any changes that you've noticed in any of those areas?
So I'll preface this by saying, because I'm department head, I only teach one class a year now, so I'm not in the classroom.
And the past couple of times that I've taught, it's been a graduate class where I think the
the impact of this, at least in our discipline, is not felt as keenly as in some others.
But I did run a workshop for our department last fall where really we called it a think shop where we could just kind of talk through what we were concerned about and how we were grappling with it.
I think where we are in the moment right now is trying to balance between the impulse to assume that students are cheating
when they're using AI.
And the opposite impulse, which I think characterizes some of the other programs on campus where it's an expectation that you will use AI tools and that that is part of building your job skills.
So we're kind of polar opposites in many of the humanities fields compared to some of the others, for example, maybe over in the Mays Business School where it's expected that you'll become conversant with these AI tools.
So
I think that's where we are at this moment.
A few years ago, I think it was, everybody's cheating with AI.
And that was the biggest concern.
One of the other issues for us right now is intellectual property rights.
As writers, as people who are generating knowledge, figuring out how to protect that from being bought and sold out from under us, basically.
But I think also reminding students that, I mean, it's important to me that students continue to understand that the LLMs are really, they're predictive, right?
And so they're only as good as what they have been told.
And that is not even close to what the human brain is capable of.
And so there is still so much that people can do and think and produce that is not possible for a predictive model to be able to achieve.
And when I do teach undergraduate courses, I show students this kind of in real time.
We'll take some very obscure example from a book, something that we think that the AI tool will not know anything about.
We put it in there and it comes back with a really smart answer about this thing or this person.
Sounds kind of right, but as soon as we begin to scratch beneath the surface, we realize it's just making stuff up.
It's telling us what it thinks we want to hear, not what is true about the person or the thing or the event.
So I think we have a long way to go to figure out where AI should be in our educational enterprise.
Mm-hmm.
I personally also have really deep ethical concerns about AI in terms of environmental impact, in terms of intellectual property rights, and in terms of reproducing bias in societies.
I think there's a lot of things that the next time I teach an undergrad class and I talk to them about it, I want to make sure that my students are at least aware of the cost
of using these tools.
There are real costs that I think we are being incentivized to look past.
So that's kind of where I stand.
Oh, thank you.
That's literally just feeding my personal curiosity.
Everybody has a different, I've noticed a lot of, in the humanities side, people are like leery and arms-like kind of thing, but on the tech side, the more tech side, they're gung-ho about it, which is very scary to me.
Well, and as a writer, I know some of my colleagues who are maybe in the sciences, they are amazing, accomplished researchers and teachers, but writing is not their strong suit, or they feel like writing is not their forte.
But I'm horrified that people don't write their own, whatever it is, memos, even.
Because that's just something that I pride myself on, and it's just such a part of who I am as a scholar that it's hard for me to imagine.
even delegating that control, that task to someone else.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I will do my last couple questions then.
I have two legacy questions coming over from Terry Anderson, as well as some other people that we have.
One is, if you were given a million dollars and you had to spend it somewhere in this university, what would that be?
What would that look like for you?
What a great question.
What would that look like for me?
I think I would endow, because you can endow things with a million dollars.
I think I would endow a legal defense center.
Ooh, okay.
Yeah.
Or some sort of, something along those lines.
And something to provide, and maybe legal defense is even a little bit too narrow, but some sort of office.
Mm-hmm.
That could provide a little bit of a safety net for students who are struggling with legal issues, maybe around immigration, things like that.
But also provide some support for students who I think fall through the cracks when they have food insecurity.
or concerns, other types of concerns that are related to their socioeconomic background.
Because I think that many times students who have those kinds of features of their background, they often don't have, they have neither the generational wealth nor the generational knowledge to know how to navigate the challenges that they're facing, whether they're financial, legal,
you know, nutritional.
So I would endow some kind of center that would provide support for people who are facing those challenges who don't know where to start.
That's awesome.
That's the first time I've heard that from anybody, so that's a great one.
And the second legacy question is, if you could give some advice to the leaders of this university, what would that be?
Trust us.
Yeah.
We were all brought here, hired here, recruited here because we're really good at what we do.
And people like me, people like Dr. Anderson, who's been here 45 years, we have given this university the best years of our lives and continue to do that because we love what we do, right?
Mm-hmm.
At least in the humanities, we're not laughing all the way to the bank in our tweed jackets with our suede elbow patches.
I don't know what people imagine that scholars are doing.
But we don't do this because we're going to get rich and famous.
We do this because we are absolutely committed to it, 100%.
So trust us to know what we're doing.
That's why you hired us.
And if you can't trust us, then I'm not sure what we're doing here.
It's not being an institution of higher education.
It's something else.
That's perfect.
Thank you so much.
Was there anything that you wanted to bring up or mention that I didn't get to?
No, I'm really glad you're doing this amazing project on the oral history.
Thank you so much for meeting with me.
It's a lot of fun.
Yeah, I'm having so much fun talking to different aspects of this university.
I bet.
Yeah.
Go ahead.